{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "After this event, Hyman Rickover testified that no “simple, easy gimmick” explains why his program had never experienced an event like this disaster. Former Dartmouth President John Kemeny chaired a commission investigating this event. William Scranton falsely reported that Metropolitan Edison claimed that “everything was under control” after this event, which occurred at a facility named for its distance from Middletown, Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this 1979 accident, the worst nuclear disaster in American history.",
      "answer": "Three Mile Island nuclear accident or disaster, meltdown, etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, the Marquesa was sent out ahead to prevent attacks from light ships. The fall of the Famagusta colony preceded this battle, which brought an end to one side’s attempt to rescue Cyprus. The Real [ray-AHL] rammed the flagship of Uluc Ali Pasha at the height of this battle. Miguel Cervantes lost an arm in this battle, which was a decisive victory for Don Juan of Austria. For ten points, name this 1571 battle where the Holy League defeated the Ottomans.",
      "answer": "Battle of Lepanto"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1944, a ship named for this figure ran aground on a sandbank in the Thames Estuary; its masts rise above the water, and it still holds nearly 3 million pounds of live explosives. Benedict Arnold replaced this man as leader of an invasion after he was killed by a burst of grapeshot to the head and thighs, contrary to the musical Hamilton, which claimed he “took a bullet in the neck in Quebec.” For ten points, name this Irishman who fought for the colonists during the American Revolution, leading the 1775 invasion of Canada.",
      "answer": "Richard Montgomery"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once wrote a letter to New York Congressman John J. LaFalce complaining of how “a woman can’t even carry Mace in her purse.” This man, who called for the murder of Lon Horiuchi for killing of the wife of Randy Weaver, rented a Ryder truck to carry out an attack that was co-plotted by Terry Nichols. Over 160 people were killed in a 1995 attack by, for ten points, what domestic terrorist who bombed the Alfred P. Murrah building in Oklahoma City?",
      "answer": "Timothy McVeigh"
    },
    {
      "question": "The “bat-wing” floor plan that once characterized these places was described in the Kirkbride design. After a Quaker woman died in one of these places, William Tuke founded the York Retreat, which developed the “moral treatment” method used in these places. The reform of jails, schools, and these institutions was promoted by Dorothea Dix before she worked as a nurse in the Civil War. For ten points, name these facilities where patients with disorders like schizophrenia were often abused in 19th century America.",
      "answer": [
        "psychiatric hospitals or mental hospitals",
        "mental asylums",
        "insane asylums"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This treaty was signed by the British and Dutch after an agreement to terminate the successful Ostend trading company. This treaty was devised in an attempt to break an agreement of shared rule with Joseph I’s bloodline, the Mutual Pact of Succession. Since this agreement violated Salic Law, it was broken shortly after Charles VI’s death. For ten points, name this 1713 agreement that allowed for Maria Theresa to ascend the Habsburg throne.",
      "answer": "Pragmatic Sanction of 1713"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1957, this musician canceled a Soviet Union tour in solidarity with the Little Rock Nine. Kid Ory was part of this musician’s “Hot Five” band, which added Pete Briggs and drummer Al Dodds to become the “Hot Seven” in 1927. This man, the first jazz musician to reach the cover of Time magazine, won a Grammy in 1964 for his performance of “Hello, Dolly!” For ten points, name this legendary jazz trumpeter and singer of “What a Wonderful World,” known as Satchmo.",
      "answer": "Louis Armstrong"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader, who was nicknamed “the pineapple” for his heavy acne, was the target of Operation Nifty Package, in which Linda Ronstadt’s “You’re No Good” and “Welcome to the Jungle” by Guns N’ Roses were blared outside the Vatican embassy. This leader, who took power two years after the death of Omar Torrijos, was overthrown in Operation Just Cause after his role as a conduit for Colombian drug cartels was revealed. For ten points, name this military dictator of Panama.",
      "answer": "Manuel Noriega"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jesse Elliot was the second-in-command during this battle, whose combatants included the Queen Charlotte and the Caledonia. This battle was preceded by a ten day blockade of Presque Isle. One leader in this battle transferred his command to the Niagara after his original ship, the USS Lawrence, was destroyed by enemy fire. Upon his victory in this battle, that leader wrote to his superior that “We have met the enemy and they are ours.” For ten points, name this 1813 naval victory for Oliver Hazard Perry at a namesake Great Lake.",
      "answer": "Battle of Lake Erie"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city used a luxury tax to keep rents artificially low in public housing projects like the enormous Karl-Marx-Hof during a period from 1918-34 in which this city was nicknamed “Red.” Moritz Schlick organized an influential intellectual group in this city around 1918; that group, which included members like Godel and Carnap, advocated for logical empiricism and was called this city’s Circle. For ten points, name this home city of Sigmund Freud, the capital of Austria.",
      "answer": "Vienna or Wien"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Mason read this man’s last speech to the senate, which noted the South would “part in peace” if faced with “submission or resistance.” This Secretary of State for John Tyler supported the annexation of Texas, and as Vice President, this man drew the ire of Andrew Jackson when his wife Floride ignored the wife of Jackson’s Secretary of War in the Petticoat Affair. With Daniel Webster and Henry Clay, this man formed a triumvirate in the senate. For ten points, name this politician from South Carolina who promoted the doctrine of nullification.",
        "answer": "John Calhoun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Petticoat Affair, this woman was snubbed by Floride Calhoun. It was rumored her first husband, John Timberlake, was distanced from her by her second husband, Jackson’s future Secretary of War.",
        "answer": "Margaret “Peggy” Eaton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Soldiers from this former nation plotted to assassinate a losing candidate in Operation Quartz, but his victory meant the operation wasn’t necessary. Abel Muzorewa briefly led a successor state to this entity, and the Lancaster House Agreement ended a longstanding conflict in this country. Forces loyal to this country fought ZANU and ZAPU guerrillas in a civil war known as its namesake “Bush War.” Robert Mugabe gained power after the 1979 dissolution of, for ten points, what former African country now known as Zimbabwe?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Rhodesia",
          "Colony of Southern Rhodesia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This racist Prime Minister of Rhodesia signed the Internal Settlement with Abel Muzorewa in 1978 and was one of the signatories of the Lancaster House Agreement.",
        "answer": "Ian Smith"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Theophilus Cotton ordered the splitting of this feature in order to allow a portion of it to be displayed more publicly. Alexis de Tocqueville wrote how this feature’s “very dust is shared as a relic.” Thomas Faunce was the first to describe the legend about this object that John Alden was the first person to have set foot on it. William Bradford’s history surprisingly omits any mention of, for ten points, what physical object where, in 1620, the pilgrims aboard the Mayflower supposedly set foot?",
        "answer": "Plymouth Rock BONUS:OnitswaytoAmerica,theMayflower wasaccompaniedbythissmallershipthatalsotransported pilgrims. ANSWER: Speedwell 4 Yakov Zhilinsky was blamed for giving overaggressive orders in this battle. Max Hoffmann predicted that Alexander Samsonov and Paul von Rennenkampf would refuse to help each other during this battle, which was followed by an engagement at the Masurian Lakes. This battle was named after a battle 500 years earlier to “avenge” a loss at Grunwald. Erich Ludendorff rose to fame after, for ten points, what 1914 battle where Paul von Hindenburg defeated a Russian force? ANSWER: Second Battle of Tannenberg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “first” Battle of Tannenberg, fought near Grunwald in 1410, was a loss for this Germanic group that formed in the 12th century. This group still gives honorary knighthoods today.",
        "answer": [
          "Teutonic Knights or the Teutonic Order",
          "the Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician declared “There is no place for the state in the bedchambers of the nation” before decriminalizing homosexuality. This politician, who once claimed that he had used the words “fuddle duddle” when a journalist questioned him for swearing in Parliament, made French and English equal under the Official Languages Act in 1969, one of the first accomplishments in his over 15 years as Prime Minister. For ten points, name this Canadian politician who was the father of Canada’s current PM.",
        "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the 1970 October Crisis, Pierre Trudeau gave this laconic reply to a reporter who asked “How far would you go with that?” in restricting civil liberties to maintain the peace.",
        "answer": "Well, just watch me."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This king’s forces captured Minorca, leading to the execution of John Byng. Robert-Francois Damien’s attempt to kill this man was foiled by his thick winter clothes. This man’s minister Cardinal Fleury punished Jansenist priests, and his mistress supported Enlightenment philosophers like Voltaire. The saying “Apres moi, le deluge” or “after me, the flood” is attributed to, for ten points, what great-grandson of the Sun King, Louis XIV [14]?",
        "answer": "Louis XV"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This official mistress of Louis XV was depicted in several Francois Boucher [boo-shay] paintings, including one of her playing the harpsichord.",
        "answer": "Jeanna Antoinette Poisson, the Madame de Pompadour"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was the founder and first head of the insurance company Pacific Life. This man claimed that he employed a “degraded and distinct people” in the wake of their immigration boom; those Chinese-Americans were hired by this man for a project that ended with this man hammering in a spike in Utah. The Central Pacific Railroad was headed by, for ten points, what business tycoon who names a university in Palo Alto, California?",
        "answer": "Leland Stanford"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “last spike” of the transcontinental railroad was driven in by Leland Stanford at this Utah location.",
        "answer": "Promontory Summit or Promontory Point"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man annexed Nabatea after the death of its king Rabbel II Soter. This man won the Battle of Tapae before crossing the Danube River, allowing him to capture Sarmizegetusa. In 106 AD, the Dacian Empire was defeated by this man, who brought the Roman empire to its territorial height. This man’s conquests were commemorated in a spiral relief column in the Forum. For ten points, name the second of the Five Good Emperors.",
        "answer": "Trajan or Marcus Ulpius Trajanus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After putting down the Dacians, Trajan pressed on to attack this empire to the east, capturing the city of Susa.",
        "answer": "Parthian Empire"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "James Madison",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Home state of Madison, as well as early American presidents George Washington and Thomas Jefferson.",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of Constitutional amendments authored by Madison.",
          "answer": "Bill of Rights"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who served as Madison’s Secretary of State and his successor as President.",
          "answer": "James Monroe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of papers that James Madison co-wrote under the pseudonym Publius in support of the U.S. Constitution.",
          "answer": "Federalist Papers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Party founded by Madison and Jefferson on whose ticket Madison ran for the presidency.",
          "answer": "Democratic-Republican Party do not"
        },
        {
          "question": "Representative who names two bills dealing with attacks on American shipping that Madison signed.",
          "answer": "Nathaniel Macon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Candidate who opposed Madison in his first bid for the presidency.",
          "answer": "Charles Cotesworth Pinckney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Slave owned by Madison who bought his freedom with Daniel Webster’s help and published a memoir in 1865.",
          "answer": "Paul Jennings"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Irish War of Independence",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country from which Ireland sought its independence.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "Great Britain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city used by the Irish Republic, the Irish Free State, and modern Ireland.",
          "answer": "Dublin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holiday that names a 1916 Rising led by Patrick Pearse.",
          "answer": "Easter Rising"
        },
        {
          "question": "Day of the week nicknamed “Bloody” after a 1920 massacre at a Gaelic Football game.",
          "answer": "Bloody Sunday"
        },
        {
          "question": "British Prime Minister who led Britain during the War and represented Britain at the Paris Peace Conference.",
          "answer": "David Lloyd George"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paramilitary force nicknamed for the color of their uniforms, composed primarily of World War I veterans.",
          "answer": [
            "Black and Tans",
            "Royal Irish Constabulary Special Reserve"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Left-wing political party that declared the breakaway Dail Eireann in 1919, starting the War of Independence.",
          "answer": "Sinn Fein , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of that political party, who chaired the Irish delegation at treaty talks in 1921.",
          "answer": "Arthur Griffith"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century Egypt",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that Egypt fought in a 1948 war, shortly after it declared its independence.",
          "answer": "Israel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Canal that connects the Mediterranean and Red Seas that was nationalized in a 1956 “crisis.”",
          "answer": "Suez Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian President who nationalized the canal in 1956.",
          "answer": "Gamal Abdel Nasser"
        },
        {
          "question": "Construction project that was to be financially supported by the US and UK; their withdrawal led to the canal crisis.",
          "answer": "Aswan High Dam"
        },
        {
          "question": "under Mohamed Morsi.",
          "answer": "Muslim Brotherhood"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last ruling king of Egypt, who abdicated in favor of his infant son in a 1952 coup d’etat.",
          "answer": "King Farouk I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Briefly-lived union of Egypt and Syria that existed from 1958 to 1961.",
          "answer": "United Arab Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dominant political party between the World Wars; it dissolved in 1952.",
          "answer": "Wafd Party"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Adam Hochschild alleged that the country ruled by this man underwent a “Great Forgetting” after his death. A Mark Twain pamphlet titled for this man’s soliloquy publicized the practice of severing human (20 pts)",
        "hands that was carried out by this leader’s military force, the Force Publique. The Stokes Affair damaged this ruler’s reputation, as did the Casement Report, which announced the brutal treatment of (10 pts)",
        "rubber plantation workers in a state that this leader established during the Berlin Congress. The Congo Free State was ruled by, for ten points, what Belgian king?"
      ],
      "answer": "Leopold II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Followers of this denomination travel on the Arba’een pilgrimage, one of the largest in the world. That event is part of this denomination’s remembrance of the death of Husayn ibn Ali at the Battle of Karbala, the (20 pts)",
        "Mourning of Muharram, which includes the day of Ashura. This denomination, which includes Sevener and Twelver schools, believes that (10 pts)",
        "Muhammad appointed his son-in-law Ali as successor. For ten points, name this denomination dominant in Azerbaijan and Iran, the second-biggest denomination of Islam behind Sunni Islam."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Shia Islam",
        "Shi’ites"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To help ease the burden caused by taxes on the financing of these objects, Periandros introduced a system called the symmories. Polycrates provided forty of these objects in the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Pelusium. During the First Punic War, these were among the smaller vessels outfitted with a hook-like boarding tool called a corvus. One of these vessels provided news of defeat to the (10 pts)",
        "Athenians after the Battle of Aegospotami. For ten points, name these ancient ships named for the fact that they had three rows of oars."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "triremes",
        "triremis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Due to his struggles with dyslexia, Mike Gravel had to stop his Senate reading of these documents, which were obtained by a colleague of Anthony Russo who worked at RAND Corporation. These documents were the subject of the (20 pts)",
        "Supreme Court case New York Times Co. v. United States. These documents included a memo claiming that “[avoiding] a humiliating (10 pts)",
        "defeat” was Lyndon Johnson’s main reason to continue a certain war. Daniel Ellsberg released, for ten points, what controversial documents about the Vietnam War prepared by the Department of Defense?"
      ],
      "answer": "Pentagon Papers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author wrote a work in which Pope Innocent XII is asked to overturn the conviction of the count Guido Franceschini, The Ring and the Book. This author inserted the ironic phrase “God’s in his heaven, all’s right with the world,” in the (20 pts)",
        "“Pippa Passes” piece for the Bells and Pomegranates series. This author’s most famous poem is suspected to be about Alfonso Il d’Este, the Duke of Ferrera, and his murdered wife Lucrezia d’Medici, whom he describes as having a heart (10 pts)",
        "“too soon made glad.” For ten points, name this Victorian poet of My Last Duchess, the husband of the author of Sonnets from the Portuguese."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Browning"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This election year marked the first time a party’s national convention was televised. The winner of this election won support by claiming the 80th Congress had stuck a “pitchfork in the farmer’s back.” During this year’s Democratic convention, 30 (20 pts)",
        "southern senators walked out over a civil rights dispute and instead nominated “Dixiecrat” Strom Thurmond. In this year, a (10 pts)",
        "photograph was taken of a man holding a Chicago Daily Tribune newspaper that incorrectly reported Thomas Dewey as the victor. For ten points, name this year in which Harry Truman won a full term in office."
      ],
      "answer": "US Presidential election of 1948"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ziryab introduced toothpaste and deodorant to this peninsula from Baghdad. Hisham II ruled a caliphate on this peninsula where the hajib Al-Mansur secured power. (20 pts)",
        "Taifas were independent kingdoms on this peninsula, where Muhammed XII of the Nasrid Dynasty ruled an emirate. Cardinal Cisneros led a (10 pts)",
        "campaign against Muslims on this peninsula, which was home to the emirates of Cordoba and Granada. For ten points, name this European peninsula that was the subject of the Reconquista by Christian forces fighting for Spain."
      ],
      "answer": "Iberian Peninsula"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one war, this country favored holding the towns of Ebeltoft and Fredericia to force attackers into a defensive line known as this country’s “earthwork.” This country passed the November Constitution to exert influence over a region it promised not to (20 pts)",
        "annex, leading to the violation of the London Protocol and subsequent invasion. After this country was decisively defeated at Dybbol, it surrendered the region of (10 pts)",
        "Lauenburg. For ten points, the Treaty of Vienna was signed after an Austrian and Prussian coalition forced what Nordic country to give up Schleswig and Holstein?"
      ],
      "answer": "Denmark"
    }
  ]
}